[Music]
Welcome mental health family members and
viewers
are welcome to mental health Monday.
We're so happy that you guys are here
with us. We're excited. Today is our
grand finale for season three. So like,
yay. We've had three seasons. We've been
here for three three years. Isn't that
wild? I guess time flies when you're
having fun. That is wild. It is. We have
some And for you, those of you who are
just um starting watching Mental Health
Monday, please while we're on this break
during the summer, go back and watch
some of our old programs because we have
some good programs um for the the three
years worth of programs. So, you're not
going to want of all top different
topics on mental health. So, we are
excited that we've been able to do that
uh for three years. and just want to say
officially welcome Dr. White to uh this
evening's program. My pleasure. Thank
you for having me. Yes. And again,
welcome to all of you. Let's see.
Welcome Clint. Clint, you're number one.
Always number one, Clint. You're going
out with a bang, Clint. Yes. Yeah.
Please put in the chat where you guys
are viewing from so we can say a special
welcome to you. And as you can see,
tonight's topic is marriage and
relationships. So we are excited to talk
about that with you and also and you'll
get more information towards the end. Um
I am doing a marriage retreat a virtual
marriage retreat. So it doesn't matter
where you are in the world because you
guys are you know we have people who
wake up in South Africa and and watch
mental health Mondays or it could be in
Australia or wherever whatever time it
is for for you at that time you can be
uh part of a virtual marriage retreat.
And so we'll give you more information
on about that towards the end. But right
now we're going to be taking your
questions and comments and and and all
of that about marriage, relationships,
even being single. We want to talk about
it all. So we are here for it all. As
they say, we are here for that. So
definitely um get your questions ready.
So I want to say welcome to Shan from
Buford, Georgia. Welcome to Mental
Health Monday. We are so happy that you
are here with us today. Also, Mi Ford
from Palaski, Tennessee. Okay. Welcome.
And Jason um from Walaw Wala.
Thank you for being here. I can't see.
Okay. Yeah. Agnes and Jean. I see Agnes
Jean. Welcome, Agnes Jean. Yes. And then
I can't quite see. I know it says
Alamita, but I can't see the name
because it has MP MPG from Alamita,
California. From Alamita from from the
Bay. Oh, is that from the bay? Okay.
Alama's near uh near Oakland and Fremont
and um yeah, I have spent some time
there. Definitely Alamita, beautiful Bay
Area. So, we are just happy to have all
of you, all of you here uh with us this
evening. Um, have to say Dr. White, I'm
sure when we talk about addiction, you
probably feel like that's one of my
favorite topics because that's what you
specialize in, right? When we talk about
marriage and relationships, I'm like, h,
I'm excited because that's what I
specialize in. Um but always happy to um
we both love to share um advice that's
going to make a marriage happier which
is going to um make if a marriage is
happier the children are happier and if
the children are happier and people
other family members are happier you
know it's just a better um they could
that can help to create better human
beings for society you know to have
healthy a coming from a healthy home or
healing a making a home healthy if it's
not healthy. So, absolutely, we love to
talk about these things. So, yeah, we're
looking forward to your questions. And
if they don't put them in the chat, I'll
get the questions going because I will
Oh, yeah. I will definitely uh tap your
um expertise. Yes. All right. So, well,
we might as well start because when we
start, then they start to warm up. So,
we're we're going to start. We're going
to take that time. We're going to get
your guys' um marriage questions. Um,
we're going to help populate them by
We're going to start. So, you go ahead
and start, Dr. White. Okay.
You have a number of favorite things
that you like to remind us of. Um, for
example, you remind us to get a PhD in
your spouse, like really learn them. Um,
along the lines of that, what would you
say is another thing that you love to
remind couples about because you see
them forget it so often? Oh my goodness.
H on the spot question. Okay. The most
besides getting a PhD in your spouse,
what do I love to remind them the most?
There's so many things. Um, okay. This
is one. I don't know if it's the most,
but it's one. um that you're on the same
team.
That you're on the same team because you
know when you start bickering and
fighting, you've drawn the line and it's
like I'm going to use a basketball
analogy because you guys know I love
basketball. So it's like you're on the
war, you're the Warriors, you're the
Steph Curry and they're the LeBron
James. Like you're battling like you're
going to like you're trying to beat your
your your spouse or you know try to win
and that that's not that's not the goal.
That shouldn't be the goal. You're on
the same team. You don't have to.
They're not your um adversary. They're
your lover, your friend. And so, you
don't have to, you can speak to them
with even when you disagree, you can
speak to them with kindness and respect.
Because when you think about when uh
teammates are on the on the floor, on
the field playing, like even if they're
saying, "Hey, man, do this better." Or,
"Hey, I'm open over here or whatever."
They're not belittling them. They're not
calling them stupid. they're not, you
know, they're treating them with respect
and just, you know, letting them know
like, oh, I think you can do it like
this better or whatever. So, it's like
treating your spouse like you are on the
same team and they're not the
opposition.
Yeah, that's that's powerful. Um, I was
listening to Kevin Liry comment on what
causes a lot of relationships to fall
apart. For those of you who don't know,
he's a Shark Tank judge and very, very
fiscally minded. and he mentioned that
he was surprised to learn the role
finances played in causing relationships
to decline.
And
with what you just said,
when there's a fight over the resources,
right, and each one is trying to get the
resources to their side rather than a
collaborative attitude and saying, "No,
we're on the same team, right? Like,
let's get the resources to the places
that will move forward the agenda of the
team, right?" You can see how that
other, you know, that that mindset of
collaboration
supports the relationships and then
finances don't rip the relationship
apart. Right. Right. Yeah. It's huge.
It's huge. We have a question. Yeah.
Let's go for it. What are Oh, okay. What
are some suggestions for married couples
as it relates to postpartum depression?
I'll let you take a stab and then I'll
Sure. So with postpartum depression, we
are talking about the depression that
can be associated with pregnancy and
it's something that we're recognizing
more and more. Uh when you think about
the birth process,
it and it's really amazing that a
woman's body is designed such that it
can actually give birth. And then you
start realizing, man, what must be the
chemicals? What must be the hormones and
how must they shift as a person goes
from not having a baby, having a baby to
then giving birth to that baby. Can you
imagine the hormonal shifts that have to
take place, right? And then the power of
these hormones is that they impact the
mind and thinking. Um, so
you can see then how
easy it is for a person then to
experience a a reduction in their mood.
Um, as you think about decreased energy,
sometimes the birth outcome might not
have been what the person wanted for
whatever reason. Um, sometimes there
isn't as much support as they would want
um or need. and and all of these things
can contribute to the postpartum
experience. Well, here's where I will
say I could have done a better job with
my wife's postpartum period. I could
have done a better job. Mhm. Um I I
believe I was in med school at the time,
so I definitely had something that was
consuming my attention,
but it was in hindsight that I really
came to understand
how
energy consuming it is, how defeating it
is, how how
interesting choice of words, but how
unfulfilled it can feel being
overwhelmed by a new child. It's weird.
It's weird because like obviously you're
fulfilled but you're so set up to feel
defeated, right? Because new mom but
less energy and sometimes the support's
just not there, right? So my personal
advice to the guy um would be
do everything possible to go beyond what
you might think is reasonable. Um do
everything possible to get into the
experience and learn about what is
involved, you know, in a woman giving
birth to a child. uh because there are
not a lot of settings that really
sensitize us to that woman's experience.
There there just aren't. And when we
don't understand,
we can then minimize and miss
opportunities to be on that person's
cutting edge. Cutting edge meaning
giving exactly what's needed at the time
that it's needed. And that's a cool
thing when you can do it.
Absolutely. I agree with everything that
you said. U really getting a PhD like in
the process of what the process is of
giving birth and what your wife is going
through. Exactly what you said. Um and a
lot of times it is the hormones but it's
also the lack of sleep mixed with the
the hormones changing. I can remember
um just after like maybe two or three
days after giving well maybe a week
after giving birth just like standing
like getting ready to take a shower but
just feeling so like
a different type of depression. I don't
believe I was fully like diagnosed
postpartum, but I could feel because of
the lack of sleep and the hormones
changing like, okay, this this is this
is nothing. I've never felt this before.
Um, so all of that is happening. Um, and
it really just reminds me that um, you
know, giving birth really was meant to
be in a marriage, in a committed
relationship, because you shouldn't, a
woman shouldn't be going through that
alone. She needs all the help that she
can get at that time. Um because yes,
probably both are not getting sleep, but
the mom, if she's breastfeeding, she's
also providing nutrition uh for this
baby. And so there's just her energy is
just like really, you know, it's just
not the best. And so I agree with you
that the husband has has to really step
up and do his part to assist the mom in
every every area. things that um
not not to expect all the things that
you um expected before before she gave
birth to the baby. Um being very um just
gentle with your wife and just and
supportive so your tone is good. I mean
the things that you should be doing
anyways, but even like up that even more
um so that she's just she's already
dealing with the stress of being a a new
mom to this baby. So trying to make
everything else her load as light as
possible um especially um if she's in a
postpartum well even if she's not in a
postpartum depression but when she's
there but to the w to the to the wife um
or the the mother um I would say
definitely work talk to your doctor
about what you're going through and what
you're feeling to just see if there you
know if you're breastfeeding you know
medication may not be the best option
but you're definitely wanting to talk to
your doctor, mental health professional
if you're feeling um thoughts of
just of course self harm or harm to the
baby and all of those type of things
because postpartum depression can get to
that point. Yeah. And so you you hop on
that kind of stuff
um sort of emerently like you you really
want to make sure you get yourself into
professional attention if you're having
thoughts of death, dying, harming
yourself or harming someone else. Those
are things that really need, you know,
immediate attention. you don't just you
don't you don't ignore that kind of
stuff. Um but uh but it's it's a
profound opportunity. It's a profound
opportunity to be there for your spouse.
It's a profound opportunity. And if you
nail it, man, uh yeah, you're not
forgotten. Right. Because I'll tell you,
when you haven't, that's not forgotten
either. Right. Right. Right. Right.
All right. Let's see. What would you
suggest is the best way to keep the
heart rate down, inner calm when a
person avoids communicating about
uncomfortable conversations?
I I would like to answer that and Dr.
White, you could do a follow-up as well.
Um, so my favorite thing that I like to
teach individuals, definitely couples,
uh, when you're in a in a heated situ
heated conversation or, you know, um,
you definitely want to activate your vag
nerve. Then your vagus nerve is the uh
longest nerve um that runs through the
the central nervous system and I think
the body. Correct me if I'm not wrong
about that. I think it's the largest
largest nerve that runs through the
body, but definitely through the central
nervous system. And so the vagus nerve
when it's activated can and that that
brings your heart rate down um and keep
and helps you to just calm down. It's
just it's just amazing what it can do.
And so you can do that through
breathing. I like to teach people to do
the four, seven, nine. So, take a deep
breath for four counts, hold it for
seven counts, and blow it, you know,
blow it out of your mouth for nine
counts as if you're trying to empty all
your all the air in your lungs. And I
like I like for people to do it two or
three times just to practice that so
when a situation does happen, they're
kind of uh more prepared to go in that
direction. But definitely do the
breathing and that opens up when you
slow when you do activate the vagus
nerve it opens up your prefrontal
cortex. This is the adult part of your
brain. So you're going to respond like
an adult when you do that because when
you don't do that and you're like have
the amygdala firing off and you're
afraid and you're scared and you're and
then other parts of your brain that are
just your emotions are just mad and
angry. You're not going to respond like
an adult. you're going to respond like a
child and you'll do stu say stupid
things, do stupid things that you're
probably going to regret later and have
to apologize for. So, it's much better
to just breathe 479. There's different
breathing techniques. Um, and then put
yourself on a timeout, a little adult
timeout, then respond. Wow. Wow. That
was nice. That was really really
powerful because you're talking about a
tool where it's if you take a good
therapeutic breath, it's almost hard to
stay like elevated, you know, right? You
do this right.
[Music]
It works.
I mean, it it's just amazing. Now, the
thing I'll add to that, um, the thing
I'll add to that since you went the
physiological route and she stole my
answer. Um, I want to go the other
route. I'm gonna go the other route and,
um, I'll talk about the the spiritual.
Okay. Um, since a lot of our audience is
Christian, I'm I'm comfortable, you
know, mentioning this. Um,
we as Christians believe that there's
God and we believe there's Satan. and we
feel like Satan is active in this world
causing turmoil. One of the things that
helps keep me calm in arguments is
remembering
that Satan would love to escalate your
argument. He would love to do that. And
so there are thoughts that will come to
you that often are not helpful.
So what I talk about is AM frequency
versus FM frequency. M AM frequency is
when God is trying to talk to you. All
right. Yeah. And the the importance of
AM frequency is it really underscores
the importance of your devotional life
because when you get up early in the
morning and you do your devotion, it
attunes you to AM frequency.
What is God saying? Yeah. You know, I I
I know you're upset with her, but
remember, she does nice things.
Um I I I know he's not at his best right
now, but he's the father of your
children and you know he'll come around
like am frequency. Now what's on the
same you're on the same team. We're
we're on the same team ultimately you
know um other things like and we have a
big function tomorrow. It would help if
we weren't fighting right now. What's FM
frequency? FM frequency. There he goes
again. You know there he goes again. I I
don't know why I put up with this. This
is FM frequency. Um uh you know, I've
had it. You know, I've had it. You can
barely even hear what the person's
saying. You know, that's the dumbest
statement I've ever heard in my life.
These are the thoughts whether you're
saying it or not. But now, let's let's
just pause for a second. How does that
make you feel?
Dumbest statement in the world. And he's
always these these these statements that
at their core are rich with contempt,
right? You know, it certainly isn't
going to help your heart rate
or your your your your autonomic tone.
It's not going to help. But when you can
shift perspective tone, yeah, it's it's
not going to help. When you can shift
your perspective, when you can say, "I'm
not going to be manipulated.
I'm going to I'm going to shift. I'm
going to turn from FM and I'm actually
going to turn to AM frequency. God, what
are you saying to me in this moment?
Right? Um, that's what can lead you to
remain solutionoriented
rather than letting your ego get
insulted, you can keep your eyes on
solution and making sure that you're
actually hearing one another, right?
Awesome. Awesome answer. I love that.
Um,
let's see. Is it okay for a young woman
in in a marriage to take their mother's
advice to have a secret account without
her husband knowing? And what are the
dangers of doing this, if any? Mercy.
I'll just I'll say something about this
first. Um well, we we don't know the ins
and outs of that situation, why the
mother is saying that. I mean, I would
say
normally I would say absolutely not.
that you know to do something like that
but not knowing that specific situation
and can't say that about that specific
situation. So I'm just speaking in
general um that transparency that's
something I tell every marriage
transparency is crucial. you're you're
being honest and you're not keeping a
secret on you're not keeping secrets
from your spouse. Like they need to and
I think I've said this on here before,
they need to know uh especially about
money. Especially about money. So,
because this is dealing with a a bank
account, that just I don't know sets off
alarms for me that something else is
definitely going on. It's not that's not
a good thing. Um
if you guys can couples can have two
separate bank accounts for sure but you
need to know that's what you're doing
that needs to be discussed. You don't
have like a private account like the two
shall be one. How can you become one and
there are secrets in the marriage. So
generally that's absolutely a no. I that
advice from the mom I would say would be
wrong. But not knowing this situation um
I couldn't speak of that specific
situation. I I loved your caution
because I was going to launch in and
then your your caution was like, "Wait a
second." Because I love your caution
because when we're talking about
marriage, we're talking about from
newlyweds, goooo gaga, you know, in love
one all the way to almost divorced but
married on paper. And so that's why we
can't speak to this situation. Who
knows? May maybe there's even abuse in
the relationship. I was going to say if
it's an abusive situation, then you
might be saving up. you might be saying
to escape and you're storing that away.
Well, that would make sense. It varies.
That said, I want to I want to build on
what you just said. Um
truth. Yeah. The the the foundation of
relationship is truth. And I talk about
like two dimensions of truth. The first
dimension is honesty.
Now honesty is delivering the truth if
asked the right question. Yeah, that's
honesty. But the second dimension of
truthfulness is transparency. What you
just mentioned, transparency where your
delivery of the truth is independent of
the right question. It's independent of
even a question.
You're truthful. When when when your
lover sees you, they can see through
you, right? You're transparent. Um, now
I'm not talking about cruel truth. I'm
not talking about that. But I'm talking
about alignment to where you don't have
to hide. Um, to me, that's the
foundation of intimacy is the ability to
really and truly
deliver truth. Mhm. So when we have to
hide and when we have to bend the truth
and stuff like that, it's like I feel
like that's a cancer to intimacy to the
foundation of intimacy. Yeah, there's
definitely there's definitely something
much deeper going on underneath
um something like that. There's a you
know there's something much deeper
much deeper. But again, not knowing that
situation specifically, I think those
were the best answers we could give on
that one. Exactly. You know, as you guys
are thinking of more questions, I just
want to say and maybe Amry, you could
put up the um the website. Uh there is a
virtual marriage retreat happening this
weekend, Hearts on Fire. Uh virtual
marriage retreat, and I am hosting that.
And um you'll be able to not only ask
these type well you will be able to ask
these type of questions but you're going
to be learning so much um in some of the
and definitely in some of the areas that
we're we're talking about right now. And
um it's eight hours worth of training.
Eight hours worth of training. And I
have to say that it's you're going to
get a lot. You're going to get a lot.
There's this is the third one couples
have been blessed. they have um just
implemented some of these principles
into their marriage and I don't get like
monthly reports from the first one was
like a year and a half ago but I know
that many of them said that they are
doing very well and adding the tips and
the using the tools that they learned um
in the hearts on fire virtual marriage
retreat. So if you and your spouse are
are interested in that uh definitely can
give your marriage a boost. Um, I used
the analogy I think in one of the the
advertisements like if your even if your
marriage is like just an old car, like
it's still a good running old car, but
it needs some some maintenance and work
because a old car always needs some
maintenance, uh, this is for you. If
your marriage is like uh a newer car,
but it's breaking down all the time,
this retreat is for you. Um, and and I'm
trying to think of another analogy
because I didn't think about that part,
but if your if your if your if your
marriage is like a a car that's not too
old, not brand new, but right in the
middle, um, and you're still needing to
learn better communication and all those
type of things, this retreat is for you.
So, you can just go to that website and
register for this virtual retreat. Go
ahead, Dr. White. Will it be
interactive? Oh, yeah. It's live.
It's live. So, they get to ask they get
to ask questions. Um,
and yeah, and I and I answer them.
That's phenomenal. So, I present What
happens is I present the information and
then we give this big bulk of time for
questions. That's awesome. So, that way
it's not I can get through all of the
information and not be interrupted and
that kind of thing. But, well, it's it's
funny because I think we hear about
things like this. We hear about offers
like this and we can sometimes entertain
a false sense of security like I don't
need that right and the the result of
that is we do that enough to where the
marriage gets to a condition right where
when you're finally interested
it's it's so depleted it's so emaciated
you know that
because you forfeited opportunities over
and over and over again to like
fine-tune it and get some of these
tools, right? That can be so powerful
and so impactful. Yes, we we talked
about that this week too, like that I I
was sharing with you that, you know, a
lot of times people could get a they
could get some maintenance, some tuneup
and and and be okay, right? But then
they they normally reach out to me, a
licensed marriage and family therapist,
when like the house is on fire or, you
know, they're going that their marriage
is in the in the ER and then they're
like, "Can you fix this? Well, we can
work on some things, but it's, you know,
it's a much it's a much um it's much
harder."
So, nu-ginningscounseling.com.
Yes. New Beginnings Counseling. Yes.
So, so and if if for any reason you
can't use it, um you might have a friend
that you can refer and say, "Hey, you
know what? You should really make use of
this." All right. Oh, yeah. For sure.
And if you know young couples newly
married, definitely send it their way
because I man the things I taught the
things I've learned as a marriage and
family therapist if I would have known
this known these things like in the
first year first five years okay be
honest first 10 years of marriage it
would it would have been so much easier.
Um, so definitely share with the
newlyweds, the singles. And the reason
why I say the singles, and then I know
we have more questions, but for the
singles, it's important because this is
the time for you to be pouring into
yourself to learn um these things now.
Like you're so that you're not just
stumbling into marriage when that
happens, but you already have um some
tools and knowledge going into it. I
wish I would have had that when I was a
single. Mercy. Forget newlywed. I wish I
would have known this when I was single.
Well, well, what I mean, see what
betrays it is it's funny when you think
about it, but it's so serious at the
same time. Like when think about when
you first got into the relationship,
right? There's an experience I call
virgin love, right? Where everything is
new. You know, you don't you can imagine
yelling at the person. You know, you're
so proper in front of each other. But
aside from that, there's this real love,
right? And it just gets shattered by
these like silly arguments or just the
nature of life. And
when you're single and you have the
wisdom to pursue an offer like this, it
positions you to avoid some of those
silly mistakes and forfeit that really
awesome period. in your relationship.
Yes. Oh, absolutely. I wish I would have
had it. I really And then you know
people Anyway, we can talk about that
forever. Let's take your question. Yay.
Anyway, I think there was a question up
there. I think Amar had it. Yeah. All
right. Could feelings of possible
abandonment make someone feel that way?
And what way I wonder was she talking
about cuz I'm sure that was in reference
to a statement. Um I don't I wonder if
it was in reference to whether they
should get a secret account.
But um Cassie maybe you could clarify
for us feelings of it in response to
what? Excuse me.
And then um
let's see. Yeah. So then she said, "PS,
my statement question was in reference
to the mother suggesting the bank
account secrecy, which I don't agree
with either." All right. Well, Cassie,
why don't you tell us what you really
think? I'm joking. I'm joking. I'm
joking. No. Um, feelings of abandonment.
Maybe you could talk to us a little bit
about um abandonment and and in the
context of attachment disorder.
Um, okay. Okay, we'll take it. Okay. So,
um so there's sec there's four different
attachment styles. And so I mean when
you have a sec when a when a baby at
infancy um has secure attachments
because the mother and or the father
were so loving and do and there was hugs
and warmth and security and people grow
up with secure attachments. And when
someone is born and there's not that uh
loving and doing and I'm going to hugs
again and because that makes babies feel
secure like oh I'm safe and they can
feel the the love and the cooing and the
kisses and I don't I don't know how
they're not understanding it but they're
their mind is um translating it into
security and insecurity. So when that's
not there, they have uh insecure um
attachments which uh they will have fear
of abandonment and being abandoned like
just not feeling
um you know basically not feeling wanted
or just that fear. And so, um, going
back to this question, if if if someone
if has an attachment style that, uh, is
always afraid that somebody's going to
leave them, then it's possible that even
though they're married and in a
committed relationship, they still have
that fear because they've never been to
a mental health professional to deal
with it. So, they could always feel
like, well, I better put this to the
side just in case.
Uh, but that just sets off alarms like I
said like that individual
therapy um to deal with that because
they have they're not dealing with the
issues that need to be dealt with
because it's not just showing up in
their marriage. It's it's showing up in
probably all the different spaces of
their life
because that that
attachment style goes with them wherever
they go. That's who they are.
Wow. I hope you got I hope you guys are
taking notes because that was that was a
masterclass response right there. All
right, Andre is asking, "Marriage
counseling is good and all, but
sometimes it is some it's something
mainly oriented to women. How can how
can men have desire to take part in
counseling without their spouse's
suggestion?" Um, I heard that laugh. Can
I answer this one? Yes. Yeah. Yeah. Go
for You know, it's funny that you said
that, Andre, because um I was thinking
about this because I was honestly I'm
thinking about the retreat and I was
thinking about um different little um
for the advertisement, little things I
can can use to like really pull them in.
And I'll be honest with you, let me tell
you, of course, I've had the men there
that have been drugged there by their
wife. Trust me, they're just like, "My
wife said we had to be here and you
could see it all over their face and
their body language is she's making me
come or whatever. Do you know that I can
and I'm no pride on myself. It's all
glory to God. Okay. But I can win them
over.
I like to say fair by the end of that
first session they are excited to come
back and by the end of that first
session well by the next session the
wife is like yeah he was like we got to
go to our we have to go to our
appointment. Don't forget our
appointment. We have to go. we have to
go because a lot of times the way that I
win them over is that I make sure he
feels heard and I will make sure since
he was the one that was being drugged
there, I will try to connect with him
the most cuz she's already won. Like
she's already she's already in it. So,
is I don't I'm not that I'm not
listening to the wife, but I'm really
trying to and when he when he sees that
I'm paying attention, even validating
him on some things that he's never felt
validated about, he literally sometimes
they're looking down and then they I can
they look up in my eyes and they're
like, "She's listening to me." Like,
they're like shocked. And by that time,
I already know, well, I I won. I got
them. He's he's
because you can see it like all over
their face. like and yeah, so that's
what that's what I do. So you want you
want to and finding a a therapist is
just like
shopping for anything else, right?
Meaning like you got you have to find
someone that works that you feel heard
that I'm definitely make sure and I
think all good therapists and I'm not
saying I'm the only one by any means.
All good therapists are going to
especially dealing with couples, you
have to seem balanced. you can't seem
like you're on the wife's side because
they can they kind of think especially a
female therapist they're just going to
be like oh you're just going to side
with my wife you're going to think like
her. So I have to be very
I mean when the wife is right I'm not
going to say I'm not going to make it
pretend like she's wrong but I have to
be very very balanced. So I'm saying all
that to say you have to look for a a a
couple's therapist that you feel
comfortable with and that you feel both
of you are feeling heard and listened to
by that therapist. Go ahead.
Oh, I mean everything you said was right
on point. Um, for me, I I usually work
it out with the woman. Hey, I know you
said that your spouse is hesitant. So,
just know that we're going to kind of
tilt things towards them. Kind of make
sure he feels heard. All everything that
you said, but I kind of get her in on it
so that she doesn't feel like I'm just
ganging up on her. Right. Um, and then
the other piece, Andre, is
Tante, yet again, you said it.
A lot of times
the therapeutic setting can be somewhat
hostile towards men. I said it. Okay.
Like it can be sometimes therapists
bring their own issues into it, but go
ahead. Oh, yeah. Like like you Yeah. Go.
You are you are by no means the majority
of the situation. It's like you you have
detected something and I'm glad you're
tuning into it and I think as a result
of that you're you're providing great
care because you're giving men a space
to feel heard and you're not just
beating them up in the therapeutic
setting. And obviously when you build
relationship with a person, they're
ready to hear when you hold them
accountable as well, right? But it's
like but at least you heard me. Um, and
sometimes in the therapeutic setting as
men just don't feel heard. Yeah. Um, so
you you you run up against what feels
like a bias against your perspective and
that doesn't help at all. So So I just
wanted to validate that. Um, Andre, that
you you you want a therapist that takes
the time to hear you.
Um, and and especially if men actually
take the time to show up. Like, so I
have some couples that will come on
their lunch break, right? Or it's his
lunch break, not always her lunch break.
And I mean, they're willing to stop in
the middle of the day and come to to
couples therapy. Like, yeah, you're I'm
not I don't want you to feel like this
is your beat up time. And honestly, it's
not always the man's fault anyways. I
mean, sometimes
Yeah. Well, anyways.
All right. So verse and vision said is
there a spirit of loneliness or a spirit
of depression or is it mental,
emotional, neurological or physical in
the brain? Yes. Verse. Next question.
I'm just I'm just playing. Well, because
it's kind of all those things. Um as a
Christian, I definitely believe in a
spiritual realm. Right. Right. Right.
But at the same time uh verse
there is a biological realm. Um how
we're presenting and how we're feeling
right now there's a chemical
contribution to that and it's a it's a
powerful idea when you think about it
that the way I'm feeling right now there
is a chemical influence going on in my
mind right now. There are hormones that
are in play right now that dictate how
energetic I feel or how non-energetic I
feel, how anxious I feel versus how calm
I feel. That's all chemically driven.
Um, so there's a spiritual interplay,
there's a um biological interplay, but
then there's also my perspective. If my
perspective right now is, "Oh my
goodness, there's hundreds of people
watching me and it's going to be
thousands later and man, that's so scary
and they're going to notice everything
bad about me." Like, what would be my
experience at that point? If I if I
adopt that perspective, this would not
be enjoyable at all. I would be tense.
I'd be stressed. I'd be all this other
kind of stuff, you know? Um, so yeah,
that's where there's an emotional
contribution. Um so that's why I in a
very cheeky fashion said yes verse
because all of these various things do
make a contribution. Now the mistake
that we can make sometimes is
overemphasizing the spiritual and
minimizing the the science or we can go
to this extreme as well and we can
overemphasize the science and minimize
the spiritual. We try to avoid either of
those traps and we we acknowledge the
role of the spiritual and the physical.
Right. Right. No, great question. Great
answer. Good question and good answer.
Thank you,
Deborah. Final question. Should there be
an age for marriage? For example, if one
marries too young, the marriage could be
at a disadvantage. And if a person's
marriage's too old, they're already set
in their ways. You're going to take the
first crack at that one. I can already I
can already see the Well, Deborah, yeah,
Deborah, you're definitely on to
something. But I heard um Oh, man. I
don't remember her name, actually. But I
She was a um she's a psychologist. I
don't remember her name. However,
um I heard her presentations twice. You
would think I'd remember her name, but
this was years ago.
So, uh, she shared just that she
recommends, I'm I'm quoting her, Dr. So
and So, because I can't remember her
name, but she recommends, uh,
to people to wait until they're at least
24 years old. Why does she say that, you
may ask? But according, um, to the
science, that the chromosomes,
our chromosomes are they merge closer
together. like this is fully she says
fully developed in our prefrontal cortex
and so we're making better decisions now
even with me saying what she said that
depends right I mean I'm sure that's
actually happening but everybody's life
journey and story is different so if
there was trauma then that maturity
level is not going to be where it should
be at 24 that's why we say oh somebody
might be 24 but they're acting like
they're 16 because there was trauma you
know whatever trauma happened to them
whatever so if everything is I don't
want to say perfect because nobody's
life is ever perfect but if people are
emotionally healthy and stable and there
weren't these huge traumatic events
happening to them typically according to
this study the chromosomes have formed
um and so you're they're fully formed at
24 and so uh you're more mature uh
you're wiser um all of these things and
so you guys can look for the study try
to find it out. I should be able to
quote the study if I'm saying it, but I
can't quote it right now. But that's the
principle. And so there could be
definitely some wisdom in that. Is that
like a perfect rule where it's like if
maybe God is calling two people at 21,
22 years old to get married? Can't say
like, oh, it's wrong. can't I mean it's
going to be it's going to be up to the
individuals you know but people are
literally normally more mature maybe
mid20s than they were when they were 20
or 21 or 19 or 18 on the second part of
your question. It's true. Definitely.
When you're lived a single life for 50
years and then you're bringing somebody
new into the scene, that's definitely
going to be a major shakeup versus when
you marry young and you haven't really
established your routine in life and
you're kind of finishing growing up and
establishing together. That could be
easier on that end. And then on other
spaces, it's can be harder and stressful
because maybe you haven't built your
financial u space um in the place where
you need it to be. And so you're
stressed in that. So
there's no wrong or right. You can marry
young if that's the if that's I'm going
to say as a Christian if that's what God
is calling for both of your lives. And
you can marry old if that's what God is
calling for your life and it be okay. Um
but definitely I would say it can be
harder for different reasons on both
sides of that. Go ahead. You can take
you can answer that. All right.
Brilliant response. I hope you guys were
taking notes. Um this is what I have to
add to that.
Uh the essence of being prepared to
marriage
or marry is you're able to make a
contribution
um spiritual contribution contribution
for resources. I remember going into
marriage I was about 24 25 at the time
and chromosomes were formed
right. Well, my mindset wouldn't testify
to that because my mindset was, hey,
what can I get out of this, you know,
and I think maybe I'm a maybe I'm being
a little unfair to myself because of
course I don't think I was a a complete
rascal. Um, I I I went in wanting to be
good, but I I think at earlier on I was
more focused on what I could get out of
it, and I think as I matured,
I more started getting excited about
what I could contribute. And you see
people asking themselves, "Hey man, am I
getting am I ready to to be married?
What are you prepared to deliver? What
are you positioned to deliver right
now?" And if you're not positioned to
deliver anything, maybe this could wait
till you actually um deliver something.
So advantages I see for waiting a little
later is brain development. You know,
like the the brain is not fully formed,
right? um until you're about 25. You
know that you said like you said the
prefrontal cortex so on and so forth,
right? Here's the thing to remember,
folk
rate. Yeah. 50%.
So when when something fails at such a
high level, does it make sense to take
precautions?
Yeah. We keep harping on maturity,
right?
And I'm going to drill this down to
emotional intelligence. Okay. So there's
a principle called emotional
intelligence, EQ.
The hallmark, one of the hallmark
foundational things in emotional
intelligence is self-awareness.
Self-awareness. And one of the problems
that can occur when you go into marriage
and when you go into marriage too
quickly or too early is you're not
self-aware. Right? And when you're not
self-aware, you're not set up for the
second pillar of emotional intelligence,
which is self-management.
And when you're not set up for
self-management, you're also not set up
for awareness of others. Third pillar.
And when you're not aware of others, you
can't manage others.
So when you give yourself time to really
become aware of who you are, what you're
passionate about, you reduce the risk of
starting a relationship prematurely and
then waking up one day and be like,
I don't like this.
I thought I did, but the truth is I
didn't really know myself, right? you
know, um, and that can be problematic.
So,
you can wake up after choosing perfectly
and still feel that way
because marriage is not just about I
like you and I'm drawn to you. It's on
the basis of commitment.
I'm I'm committed to you, which means
I'm not just relying on how I feel. But
all that said, it helps to be
self-aware. And so that's where maturity
can help. Now, the downside to waiting
too long, is
the most competitive options kind of get
taken quickly and earlier on. So now
when you decide, okay, well, now I'm
ready. Well, now there might be less
options. Um, especially if you wait too
long. So th those are some of the
downsides. Um, and the other piece is I
don't know that you're ever completely
ready.
Um, the key thing is you've got to be
ready to grow, right? Ready to be kind,
ready to be generous, and and ready to
recognize opportunities for your own
personal growth. If you're not mature
enough to be ready to be ready to grow
and learn,
then you're not ready for marriage.
Because you're right, none of us are
ready ready completely. Um you're gonna
you're still going to have to grow. It's
still a learning curve. You just have to
be willing like just like when you sign
up for school like you know, okay, this
is what I want to do. I'm passionate
about this. This is what I'm going to
school for. But you're still learning.
You're still growing. Um and that's
that's what marriage is like.
Definitely. All right.
Okay. Hey, what you got? Sunshine said,
"The issues with my in-laws coupled with
my husband's silence is creating
significant marital anxiety.
We were weighing whether to disengage
from family events. What's the best
path? What's the best path forward for
us? Uh, you guys need Atante's marriage
retreat this Sabbath. Uh, show up so
that you can get a more customtailored
response. that that's what I would
recommend. No, but yeah, in in addition
to that, well, I mean, I'm I'm saying
sometimes I can be cheeky, guys. You got
to forgive me, but this is just my
personality. Um, this this this deserves
a customtailored response. This deserves
like unpacking, hey, this is what's
going on and this is what's happening.
And then you could get something more,
you know, customized. Um then Sunshine
further said, "We attempted to talk
things through, but they gaslight and
pull other members against us. That's
why my husband has gone silent." I'm so
sorry to hear because I can I can I can
hear and feel the pain in that question.
Um
what what are your thoughts, Sister T?
Well, I I'm trying to figure out gone
silent with with Sunshine or gone silent
with the family. I I would want to know
that, but I'm a Assuming
given our current anxiety around family
interactions, how can we discern if
disengaging is a healthy boundary to our
mental and marriage or if there's a way
to re-engage with healthier dynamics?
Well, I would say for this part of the
the question definitely um you have to
make that decision. I mean, but what
you've shared, you definitely have um
if it's if it's causing mental stress
for you and your husband and causing
issues in your marriage and you've tried
to, you know, communicate and have a
mature, spiritual, loving conversation
with the family and they are choosing
not to change, then you can definitely
make a decision and set a boundary of
where you're going to where and when you
are going to spend time with these
individuals. if you're going to continue
to spend time with them at all. Meaning,
um, because I like to tell people, I
tell this to parents, uh, other family
members, you can lose the parent card
and the family card in the way that you,
uh, treat and respect other family
members or friends and and those type of
things. Like, you can't just treat
people horribly and think like, oh, your
family, I I have to stay here with you.
No, actually, you don't. Um, but that
has to be a decision that you that you
uh that you make and that your husband
makes. Um, and if you've spoken to them
and they're still not changing, then
that definitely sounds like you're in a
space where you have to to make a
decision on how you're going to to move
forward. But you have, this is not
telling you what to do. This is just
telling you that you have um from what
you're sharing sounds like all the right
to make that decision if that's what you
decide to do. If that if you decide
that's what's going to be healthy for
you, healthier for you as an individual.
Um and
yeah, you don't have to do that. I want
to give an example here. I think it's a
it's this is this is a one of the most
popular people probably in the world,
but and I'm going to use Michelle Obama
as an example. As you know, if you guys
followed the inauguration of of Donald
Trump, this last one, she wasn't
present. And people were just thinking
like, "Wait, you're the president's
you're the ex-president's wife. You're
supposed to be here." Months later, she
came out and said, cuz everybody's was
speculating, oh, they're having marriage
problems. All they were just speculating
all over the place, which is just
speculation. And what she was what she
said is like she knew that she had never
really put boundaries down for herself
when she was in the public eye because
that's when all that
uh the expectations were for her, you
know, because she was the first lady.
She had to do this this and that. Now
she's raised her kids. Her husband's no
longer uh the president. That
inauguration is not somewhere she wanted
to be. That that wasn't going to be good
for her her mental health. So, she
decided she put down a boundary and
decided I'm not going to be there, which
was perfectly fine, right? Because she's
not in a public servant or in public
life and not, you know, the, you know,
she's just not in that position. She
doesn't have to be there. The point of
it is is to highlight when you have to
make decisions that maybe other people
won't agree with and they're kind of
hard at times, but you have to do the
best thing for you. And so that's the
example that I'm why I'm bringing this
up because she made the best decision
that was for her mental health. She
couldn't attend and sometimes we have to
make hard decisions and she's also in
therapy so she she worked that out with
her therapist before she made that
decision. But wow. Anyway, so sometimes
we have to do that. Well, I I love your
point that
just because you're blood doesn't mean
you're entitled to be toxic, right? and
and that I must be subject to your
toxicity. I I love that point, right? Um
I love that point because uh poison is
poison. It doesn't matter who's
administering it. It's still poison. And
it's it doesn't even matter that they're
doing it accidentally. You'll still die,
right? So that's why you gonna hop in.
Well, I was just gonna say because
Sunshine answered a little more. She
said he her husband has gone silent with
his family. Well, it sounds like your
husband's already made the decision,
right? And so that's why we're just
talking about general principles rather
than speaking to that situation because
the situation is so nuanced. So, I'm
joking, but I'm serious at the same
time. Like, take advantage of this offer
where maybe now you could you would you
you would have time to unpack it and and
clarify and and then maybe get a more
meaningful response from, you know,
Sister Tante. Um but whatever the case,
yeah, I I I definitely agree with you
that we have to set the boundaries that
are in the best interest of the family
firm. I like to think of the marital
relationship as a as a as a firm. I I
think of a family as a firm. And a firm
has an agenda. It has a vision. It has a
mission. It has goals and it is entitled
to set boundaries that support the
forward movement of the firm and
be guided by that. Yes. Well said. All
right. Well, sunshine, I look forward to
seeing you there. Oh, that'd be
phenomenal. She said she I look forward
to seeing you and your husband there.
Look forward to that. Oh, that's
phenomenal. That's awesome, Sunshine.
Congrats. Yes.
Now verse said if a marriage is lifelong
learning experience why is it that many
people wait to have the assurance that
everything will be perfect before
entering marriage that's funny verse I
wish people were waiting because I don't
see people waiting I see people actually
being premature and I'm again I'm joking
verse but I wish more people were having
the mindset of I'd like to be more
prepared Because what I'm observing and
maybe my my view is biased. I'm seeing
people jumping into this thing with very
little preparation. Right. I absolutely
agree. With very little
meaningful training
um so that you just the fundamentals of
communicating. How do you communicate
when you're angry? Okay. Right. How do
you communicate when you're infuriated?
What do you do when you're infuriated?
Mhm. Um, and how do you set boundaries
and feel good about it? Like these are
like just some fundamental basic tools
that nobody teaches, right? You know,
what is what is the major thing you can
do for a man? Okay, that only a spouse
can do. What is what is that major
thing? And then the flip question, what
can you do for your spouse? What can
what can a man do for his woman that
would just really knock it out the park.
Um these are not things that are
discussed.
They're not.
And and you see people rushing into this
super highstake relationship with
minimal training and you wonder why it's
50% failure rate. Yes, it is. And it's
so sad. And those numbers are the ex
those are just the numbers. Whether
Christians or non-Christians, it's the
same numbers. And we've been saying 50%
for a while. It's actually higher than
that. Those were the old numbers. It's
higher than that. And it's it's really
sad. But um and but here's the
encouraging part. Yes. There are
subpopuls
there's subops where the failure rate is
really low. There are subops. So, for
example, when you've taken the time to
be compatible, when you've taken the
time to get some of these tools, when
there there are subops that their their
rate is pretty pretty low in terms of
the failure rate, right? And so, the
appeal, the recommendation is get into
those subops. Yes. Get some of those
tools. Um, learn that partner. Get that
time to learn the partner. um so that
you build something that lasts. Like Dr.
Gottman would say, you can be you can be
part of the masters. The masters are the
marriages that make it. You don't have
to be the disasters.
But yeah, definitely get into that to
that sub population. So yes, we are
actually all out of time, guys. When
we're talking about when we're just
taking your questions and answering
them, it's so much fun, but it goes by
so fast. Uh yes, spread the word, share
on your social media. And I just want to
let you guys know going to join Sunshine
and myself at the retreat and her we're
going to be there. But want to let you
guys know about the virtual marriage
retreat that's happening this weekend.
It starts on Friday evening, uh, 700
p.m. Central time, and then it will be
at 6:00 p.m. on on on Saturday, um,
central time. And then on Sunday, it's
at 12:00 p.m. and 5:00 p.m. Central
time. And all all the sessions are two
hours each. So, it's eight hours of
training for your marriage. Eight hours
of training. I'll be honest, you go,
you'll see on the website, the cost is
really for eight hours of training,
you're getting that for like the price
of one uh therapy session with a
licensed mental health professional or
licensed marriage and family therapist.
So, you're definitely going to want to
take advantage of that. No matter what
stage your marriage is at, you can
benefit. So, if you if it's if it's uh
stuck somewhere, you're going to benefit
from the from the things that you're
going to hear. If it's, you know, doing
fairly well and just needs some
maintenance, you're going to you're
going to benefit um from the stuff
you're hearing. And if you're single,
you're going to learn things that you
can take uh into the marriage when you
get into one. Um so, you definitely just
want to you want to check it out. So,
there you see on the um there on your
screen, it's new
beginningcounseling.com/marriage
retreat. If you just go to
newbcounseling.com, you'll find the um
area that you can click on for the
marriage retreat, but it's
nu-bgingcounseling.com.
Can I can I give my final statement?
Yes, get your final statements. And that
final statement is I'm going to give you
I mentioned the sub populations um for
that have lower rates of marriage and I
I'll give you the subopuls and the um
and the statistics. So apparently
college a college college educated
couples uh the approximate divorce rate
is 25 to 30%. Down from 50%. Okay.
Religious practicing couples 20 to 30%.
Married after 25 asante was talking
about 25 to 30%. Couples who cohabitated
only after engagement
uh divorce rate 30%. Uh let's see
and married under age 20 is like 60 to
70% and premarital cohabitating so no
engagement 45 to 50%. Wow. So those send
me those send me those numbers. Was that
on chat?
You know it. You know it. Okay. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah. Because I Yeah. I want to
send those numbers to somebody. Somebody
was asking me about that the other day.
So I will I will send this right over to
you. Yes. So, Sister Tante, this is it's
all it was a pleasure uh working with
you in season 3. Yes, always always a
blessing to work with you, too. And
guys, we will be back for a brand new
season at the beginning of September.
And yeah, we're going to do even bigger
and better things. We're going to have
more special guests. Yes. Uh so, I think
you should be looking forward to that.
Um but during our summer break, please
please please go back. We'll be um
airing some of these on Monday nights,
but you can go back on your own. Just go
to mental health um mental health
Mondays on on YouTube um and make sure
it's our uh mental health Monday. Um so
that uh you will be able to watch some
of our older programs. Can you guys
still hear me? We can. It's It's showing
It's not showing your picture. Yeah,
that's okay. You guys know what I look
like, so you're just hearing my voice.
We're hearing your voice. and and we
were and we were ending. So anyways, all
right. Well, you guys have a good
evening and I can't wait to see you back
here um in September when we come back.
But please go back and view some of the
programs that you've missed over the
three years. Take care, guys. And bye,
Clint. Yeah. Bye, Clint. We'll see you.
Take care. Bye. All right. Bye. Bye.